Moving on to the thyroid gland,
the first disorder is thyroglossal duct cyst.
In order to understand this,
you've got to remember that the thyroid develops
at the base of the tongue,
and then it travels along the thyroglossal duct
to the anterior neck.
Now, normally, this thyroglossal duct should involute.
However, if it persists,
you can then get cystic dilation of that duct,
which would result in a thyroglossal duct cyst.
And, of course, this would present as an anterior neck mass.
It's particularly high-yield
because it goes into a little bit of embryology.
Lingual thyroid is when you have persistence of thyroid tissue
at the base of the tongue,
so you don't get that descent of the thyroid tissue
to the anterior neck,
and this would present as a base of tongue mass.
And, again, that's particularly high-yield,
again, tying into embryology.
Hyperthyroidism is when you have an increased level
of circulating thyroid hormone.
This would increase the basal metabolic rate
and also increase the sympathetic nervous system activity.
Very high-yield to note.
Board examiners like you to know
how it increases the basal metabolic rate.
It increases synthesis of sodium-potassium ATPase,
whereas the increased sympathetic nervous system activity
is due to expression of beta-1 adrenergic receptors.
Again, both of these are high-yield,
sodium-potassium ATPase and beta-1 adrenergic receptors.
Now, the clinical features are going to be based
on an increased BMR,
so the way I think about this,
the body goes into overdrive.
You get weight loss despite increased appetite,
heat intolerance and sweating.
Again, you're burning a lot of ATP,
which is going to generate heat.
The patients get tachycardic with increased cardiac output.
Again, they've got that increased
sympathetic nervous system activity.
Arrhythmias, for example, AFib,
can also occur, especially in the elderly.
They get tremor, anxiety, insomnia,
heightened emotions, staring gaze with lid lag,
diarrhea with malabsorption.
Again, the idea here is that the gut's sort of moving
a little bit faster as well.
Patients with hyperthyroidism can develop oligomenorrhea.
They get bone resorption with hypercalcemia.
This could eventually lead to osteoporosis,
and they get decreased muscle mass with weakness.
Finally, the patients can get hypocholesterolemia.
This is particularly high yield.
The examiners like you to know that you get hypocholesterolemia
with hyperthyroidism and hyperglycemia.
And the idea here is that the thyroid hormone
causes both gluconeogenesis and glycogenolysis,
resulting in extra sugar in the blood.
The most common cause of hyperthyroidism is Graves' disease.
This is where you have an IgG antibody
that stimulates the TSH receptor.
When you stimulate the TSH receptor,
you increase the production of thyroid hormone,
and you also increase the release of thyroid hormone.
So two things are going to occur,
increased production plus increased release.
This is the most common cause of hyperthyroidism,
as I've already stated,
and it classically occurs in women of childbearing age.
Again, this is the classic demographic
for an autoimmune disease.
Clinically, the patients are going to have hyperthyroidism.
Again, you have increased production
and secretion of thyroid hormone.
They get a diffuse goiter.
As this antibody is stimulating the TSH receptor,
that's going to cause massive hyperplasia
and hypertrophy of the thyroid diffusely,
resulting in a diffusely enlarged thyroid.
And the word goiter refers to an enlarged thyroid.
And they get epitophthalmos and pretibial myxedema.
Now, this is very important to note and very high yield.
This is not due to the hyperthyroidism.
It is due to the fact that the patients have an antibody
that stimulates the TSH receptor.
So the idea here is that the fibroblasts behind the eye,
as well as the fibroblasts over the shin,
they have TSH receptors.
And so in response to this antibody,
they actually begin to secrete excess glycosaminoglycans,
which then results in exophthalmos,
because the eye gets pushed forward,
and a pretibial myxedema.
Edema here refers to the fact that it looks like
there's swelling of the tissue,
but the word mix refers to the fact that
it's not due to water,
but instead it's due to glycosaminoglycans,
or a mixoidy substance.
And clinically, they classically describe this
as a doe-like appearance,
so that when you press over the shin,
you actually can feel a doe-like consistency to the tissue.
Here's a picture of Graves' disease.
You can clearly see that this is a goiter,
an enlarged thyroid,
and you can see that it's diffusely enlarged.
This is a histologic image
taken from a thyroid with Graves' disease,
and you can clearly see that there's hyperplasia of the follicles.
Notice how large they've become.
One of the very high-yield findings here
is that you also get scalloping of the colloid.
In order to understand this,
look at this follicle here that I'm outlining.
This is normal.
Notice that the colloid in this follicle,
the pink material,
is totally up against the blue epithelium
with no really clear white space.
However, notice that in this follicle here,
you clearly have epithelium,
but you've got this white space in between,
and this white space kind of appears scalloped like this,
and so they call that scalloping of the colloid,
and that's a particularly classic finding in Graves' disease.
Now, of course,
these patients are going to be producing excess thyroid hormone,
so there will be both an increase in total and free T4.
The TSH will go down,
and that's because the free T4
will down-regulate thyroid-releasing hormone receptors
in the anterior pituitary.
Recall that the anterior pituitary
secretes thyroid-stimulating hormone,
but only in response to thyroid-releasing hormone
that comes from the hypothalamus.
And so what T4 does
is that it down-regulates these receptors
so that the anterior pituitary
will then no longer be able to receive this signal,
and therefore will produce less TSH.
The patients will also have hypocholesterolemia.
I've already explained that,
and they'll have an increased serum glucose.
I've already explained that as well.
The treatment for Graves' disease includes beta blockers.
Again, you're trying to block the effects
on the sympathetic nervous system.
Thyomite is another treatment.
This is a drug that has the ability to block peroxidase.
Let's go back and remind ourselves
that this is the follicular cell of the thyroid.
Remember that the cell takes tyrosine,
and it converts tyrosine into thyroglobulin,
and then the thyroglobulin is pushed off
into the follicular lumen.
This is where the colloid would be.
And then at the same time,
the cell takes iodide from the blood
and brings it into the cell,
and then crosses it over to the follicular lumen,
where it undergoes oxidation and becomes I2.
Remember that the thyroglobulin and the I2
are then added together
in a step called organification,
and that's going to result in thyroglobulin
with monoiodotyrosine and diiodotyrosine.
And of course,
the mono and the di will be coupled together,
and that's going to then produce thyroglobulin
with T3 when mono and di are coupled together,
or T4 when the di and di are coupled together.
Now, important to note that all of these steps here,
the oxidation, the organification, and the coupling,
these are all catalyzed by peroxidase.
And so if you block peroxidase,
obviously you're going to block the ability
to produce a thyroid hormone.
And so that's how thioamide works.
Another possibility would be to use radioiodine
to ablate the thyroid.
The idea here is if you give radioiodine,
of course, that would be taken up
by the follicular cells of the thyroid,
which would then result in destruction
of the thyroid cells because of the radioactivity,
and so you would ablate or destroy the thyroid gland.
The thyroid storm is the feared complication
of Graves' disease.
This is when you have excess catecholamines
and massive hormone,
usually due to some sort of stress,
like surgery or childbirth.
The patients can present with arrhythmia,
hyperthermia, and vomiting
with a hypovolemic shock,
and this is treated with PTU beta blockers and steroids.
Recall from pharmacology, particularly high yield,
that PTU inhibits peroxidase-mediated oxidation,
organification, and coupling,
as I've already explained.
All three of those steps are also going to be inhibited by PTU.
In addition, PTU inhibits the peripheral conversion
of T4 to T3.
Recall that the major hormone released
by the thyroid gland is T4,
and then T4 gets converted peripherally to T3,
which is the more active form.
And so PTU will also block the peripheral conversion
of T4 to T3.
Multinodular goiter is an enlarged thyroid gland
with multiple nodules.
Again, the goiter refers to an enlarged thyroid gland,
and the multinodular means that you've got multiple nodules.
It's due to a relative iodine deficiency.
For example, some foods can induce an iodine deficiency,
et cetera, which then creates a focal nodular goiter
within the thyroid gland.
This is usually non-toxic,
meaning that the patients are euthyroid.
However, regions can rarely become TSH independent,
especially on board exams,
and that would then result in something called a toxic goiter,
where the thyroid gland begins to secrete excess thyroid hormone,
but not under the control of TSH.
Here's a picture of a multinodular goiter.
What you see here is you've got enlargement of the thyroid gland,
but you can see that it's composed of a bunch of these nodules.
Hypothyroidism refers to low thyroid hormone.
This can occur in neonates or it can occur in children and older adults.
When it occurs in neonates or infants, it's called creatinism.
Creatinism refers to a constellation of findings
in which the children have mental retardation.
Remember that thyroid hormone is necessary for normal brain development.
They also get short stature with skeletal abnormalities,
and that's because thyroid hormone is also necessary for normal skeletal development.
They can have coarse facial features, an enlarged tongue, an umbilical hernia.
These are some classic findings in a creatine child.
Now, the causes would be maternal hypothyroidism during early pregnancy.
Of course, the fetus then would not see enough thyroid hormone.
Thyroid agenesis.
If the infant does not form a thyroid gland,
that could result in hypothyroidism during infancy.
Dishormonogenetic goiter.
This is when patients have deficiency in the ability to produce thyroid hormone.
High yield for board exams, the most common enzyme that's deficient
is going to be thyroid peroxidase.
And remember that peroxidase is important for oxidation, organification, and coupling.
And so, of course, you wouldn't be able to produce thyroid hormone,
which would then again result in creatinism in the neonate.
And finally, iodine deficiency.
If the infant doesn't have access to iodine, that could also result in creatinism.
Myxedema is hypothyroidism in an older child or adult.
Clinical features here include myxedema.
Myxedema, again, refers to the fact that the tissue appears edematous.
However, instead of having fluid, it has a dough-like consistency to it.
And that's due to an increase in glycosaminoglycans in the skin and the soft tissues,
especially in the larynx, giving them a deepening of their voice and in the tongue.
And those are two classic areas for board examinations.
Again, the larynx giving deepening of the voice and an enlarged tongue.
Now, the patients who have hypothyroidism are going to have a decreased basal metabolic rate
and decreased sympathetic activity.
So they get weight gain despite a normal appetite.
They get slowing of mental activity, muscle weakness, cold intolerance with decreased sweating.
Again, they're burning less ATP.
And they can have bradycardia with decreased output.
The decreased cardiac output could result in shortness of breath and fatigue.
The patients get oligomenorrhea, hypercholesterolemia, so that's important, and constipation.
It's as if the gut slows down.
Now, what are some causes?
They include iodine deficiency.
If you don't have iodine, you can't make thyroid hormone.
Hashimoto's thyroiditis.
This is the most common cause of hypothyroidism in regions of the world where iodine is sufficient.
And basically, it's an autoimmune destruction of the thyroid gland.
Some drugs, like lithium, can cause damage to the thyroid.
And finally, if the thyroid was removed surgically or there was radioablation, for example,
if the patient had Graves' disease and you radioablated the thyroid, that could then result,
of course, in hypothyroidism, assuming that the patient was not taking thyroid replacement hormone.
Next topic is thyroiditis.
The first of these is Hashimoto's thyroiditis.
This is where you have autoimmune destruction of the thyroid gland.
It's associated with HLA-DR5.
That's particularly high yield.
Again, this is the most common cause of hypothyroidism, where iodine levels are sufficient.
Clinical features are that it can initially present with hyperthyroidism, but eventually
progresses to hypothyroidism.
Now, the idea here is that let's pretend this is a graph of time.
Let's pretend here the patient is normal thyroid.
Now, when they get Hashimoto's, what's going to first happen is they're going to destroy
the current thyroid follicles.
And as they do that, some of the thyroid hormone will actually leak out into the blood, resulting
in an initial hyperthyroidism.
Now, as they continue to destroy the thyroid, then the amount of thyroid hormone will decrease,
decrease, decrease.
And so they may eventually come back to a point where they're euthyroid, but actually they're
on their way down and they're becoming hypothyroid.
And so eventually they'll become hypothyroid.
And that's what I say here.
It can initially present as hyperthyroidism, but eventually progresses to hypothyroidism.
When that occurs, there'll be a decrease in T4, and of course that would result in an increase
in TSH.
Because remember that T4 controls a number of TRH receptors on the anterior pituitary.
Again, recall that when the T4 goes down, the TSH goes up, and that's because if this
is the anterior pituitary, it's these thyroid-releasing hormone receptors that are going to be increased
when there is less T4.
And again, that would result in an increased production of TSH by the anterior pituitary.
Often present in the patient's serum are antithyroglobulin and antimicrosomal antibodies.
These are signs of thyroid damage.
They do not mediate the disease.
Rather, they are markers that the thyroid has been damaged.
Here is a histologic image from a patient with Hashimoto's thyroiditis.
Notice that there's an abundant amount of chronic inflammation, and that focally you
get formation of germinal centers.
That's particularly high yield.
You need to know that you get chronic inflammation with formation of germinal centers.
And in addition, some of the cells that normally surround the thyroid follicle are turning pink.
And so you can see that there's this increased pink color to the cytoplasm of these cells,
and that's called herthal cell change.
And so these patients get chronic inflammation with germinal centers and herthal cells.
Now, I'd also like to remind you that patients that have Hashimoto's thyroiditis,
they have an increased risk for B-cell lymphoma.
Again, the idea here is you've got these germinal centers,
so you're also going to be generating post-germinal center B-cells,
which would eventually form something called the marginal zone.
Recall this from the white blood cell lectures.
And so you can get a marginal zone lymphoma,
and that, again, is a complication of Hashimoto's thyroiditis.
And so if you've got a patient with long-standing Hashimoto's on the board exam,
and they present with an enlarging thyroid gland, think about a B-cell lymphoma.
Subacute, decorvains, granulomatous thyroiditis.
Some people call this subacute.
Some call it granulomatous.
Some call it decorvains.
Just put all the words together and make it easy.
Subacute, decorvains, granulomatous thyroiditis.
Again, subacute implies that it occurs after an acute process,
and so this actually occurs after a viral infection.
The granulomatous tells you that you're going to get granulomatous inflammation.
Now, this inflammation can present with transient hyperthyroidism.
However, it's limited, and it does not progress.
It does not progress to hypothyroidism.
Perhaps the most high-yield point on this slide is that they have a tender thyroid.
If a young woman comes in and has a tender thyroid,
this would be one of the key things on your differential.
And so this is particularly unique.
We haven't really covered anything where we had a tender thyroid.
And so, again, tender thyroid.
Think about subacute decorvain, granulomatous thyroiditis.
Rydell's fibrosing thyroiditis.
This is when you get chronic inflammation with extensive fibrosis of the thyroid.
It presents as hypothyroidism.
But more importantly, especially for board exams,
they have a hard-as-wood, non-tender thyroid.
Hard-as-wood thyroid is sort of the buzz phrase here.
In that case, you think about Rydell's fibrosing thyroiditis.
Now, it's very important to note, especially for board examinations,
that these patients get fibrosis that not only involves a thyroid,
but can extend to local structures, for example, the airway.
And so the classic history on a board examination would be that the patient has a hard-as-wood thyroid
and also has involvement of local structures.
Now, when you have a history of a firm thyroid with involvement of local structures,
you would really, one of the other things to think about would be carcinoma.
And in particular, there is a type of carcinoma,
which we're going to cover in a moment, called anaplastic carcinoma.
Anaplastic carcinoma often spreads outside of the thyroid and invades, for example, the airway.
However, anaplastic carcinoma of the thyroid is a disease of older people,
whereas Rydell's fibrosing thyroiditis is classically a young female.
So this is very high yield to note.
If you've got a thyroid lesion that involves local structures in a young patient,
you're thinking about Rydell's fibrosing thyroiditis.
If you had the same clinical history, but the patient was 70 or 80, for example,
then you'd be thinking about anaplastic carcinoma.
Of course, you could do a biopsy to prove this.
However, on board exams, this is a particular high yield distinction to be made.
Thyroid neoplasia refers to a tumor formation within the thyroid.
This classically presents as a distinct solitary nodule.
Thyroid nodules are much more likely to be benign than they are malignant.
When a patient has a thyroid nodule that you're worried about,
you can do a radioactive uptake study.
When you do a iodine radioactive uptake study,
you would see increased uptake in, for example, Graves' disease or nodular goiter,
whereas you would have decreased uptake in adenomas and carcinomas.
Now, when there's decreased uptake, that would then warrant a biopsy.
Very high yield to note for board exams.
The key mechanism by which you biopsy the thyroid is FNA.
Examiners like to ask you, what's the mechanism of sampling the thyroid?
FNA, fine needle aspiration.
You don't want to biopsy the thyroid because it's a very bloody organ,
and when you biopsy it, it will bleed like crazy.
So instead, you simply stick a needle in, and you pull out some cells,
and you analyze them under the microscope.
The first of the neoplastic disorders is follicular adenoma.
This is a benign tumor of follicular glands.
Now, one of the very high yield points to note
is that these glands will be surrounded by a fibrous capsule.
I'll show you a picture of that in a moment.
But rarely it can secrete thyroid hormone.
Here's a picture of a follicular adenoma.
Here's the normal thyroid.
Notice that it's made up of all of these follicles
with this pink material called colloid.
And here is the tumor.
This area here that I'm marking with a T is the tumor.
Now, of course, the tumor is also making follicles,
hence the term follicular adenoma.
However, notice that there's this dense pink capsule
clearly demarcating this tumor from the rest of the thyroid gland.
And again, that's the hallmark of follicular adenoma.
You've got creation of all these follicle-like spaces,
but it's clearly surrounded by a dense capsule.
Moving on to carcinoma, there's four types,
and you need to spend a couple moments to burn this into your mind.
Papillary, follicular, medullary, anaplastic.
It's worth sort of repeating this over and over again
until you memorize it.
Papillary, follicular, medullary, and anaplastic.
And so papillary carcinoma is the most common type of thyroid carcinoma.
Represents 80% of thyroid carcinoma.
Very high yield to note that exposure to ionizing radiation in childhood
is a major risk factor.
Classic example would be a child who was radiated for severe acne.
And so if you radiate the face,
which was one of the treatments used for severe acne decades ago,
then you'd also be radiating the neck,
which means that you'd be radiating the thyroid.
Again, very high yield.
Ionizing radiation increases the risk for papillary carcinoma.
Here's a histologic image of papillary carcinoma.
And classically, papillary carcinoma will form papillary finger-like projections.
However, what's important to note is that the nuclear features
are what define papillary carcinoma.
And so what you would classically see in the nucleus
is something called orphan anti-eyed nuclei.
And so the idea here is that if this is the nucleus,
notice that there's this white clearing in the center of the nucleus,
and these are called orphan anti-eyed nuclei
because you get this white clearing in the center of the nucleus.
In addition, another feature will be the presence of nuclear grooves.
Can you see that in this nucleus, for example,
there's this line or this groove within the nucleus?
In addition, for example, here in this nucleus,
notice that there's this line or this groove within this nucleus.
And so those are called nuclear grooves,
and they are also a sign of papillary carcinoma.
Now, because you classically get papillary architecture,
you can get calcification of that papillary architecture,
which would then result in a simoma body.
Again, a simoma body is a concentric, layered calcification,
and so you can kind of see the circles of calcification.
Especially notice here, you can clearly see the layering of the calcium
in this particular part of the simoma body.
Now, papillary carcinoma classically spreads
to the cervical nodes within the neck.
However, even when it spreads to the lymph nodes,
it has an excellent prognosis.
Follicular carcinoma is a malignant proliferation of follicles.
Now, similar to a follicular adenoma,
it would be surrounded by a fibrous capsule.
However, the follicles will invade through the capsule.
Very high yield to note.
In follicular adenoma and follicular carcinoma,
you have a tumor of follicles
that is surrounded by a fibrous capsule.
However, in follicular carcinoma,
the cells will invade through the capsule,
and that's the hallmark of follicular carcinoma.
And board examiners love to go after that.
And so here's a picture of a thyroid just showing you what we mean.
You can clearly see that there's this dense capsule
surrounding this tumor,
and the capsule should have extended here.
But notice that the tumor has extended here beyond the capsule.
And so the spread of cancer beyond the capsule
indicates that you have a follicular carcinoma.
Now, I would like to use this image
to highlight one more high yield board point.
And that is, if you were to stick a needle into this thyroid
and pull it out,
what you would pull out are follicular cells or follicle-like cells,
you wouldn't really be able to assess
what's going on with the capsule.
And so therefore, you need to know that FNA biopsy
or fine needle aspiration biopsy
cannot distinguish between follicular adenoma
and follicular carcinoma.
And that's because the only way to make that distinction
would be to see the capsule.
And to see the capsule,
I would either need to see the growth specimen
or I might need to examine the entire capsule
under the microscope
to make sure that there is no microscopic invasion.
But again, very high yield to note
for the purposes of board examinations
that FNA, fine needle aspiration,
cannot make the distinction
between follicular adenoma and follicular carcinoma.
Another very high yield principle
with follicular carcinoma
is that follicular carcinoma likes to go to the blood
and it spreads hematogenously.
Now, that's a little bit of a deviation
from a general principle
because remember that the general principle
is that carcinoma likes to spread to lymph node.
However, this is a carcinoma
that likes to go to blood.
Remember that there are four carcinomas
that like to do that classically
for board exam purposes.
Renal cell carcinoma likes to go to the renal vein
and spread to the blood.
Hepatocellular carcinoma likes to go to the hepatic vein
Follicular carcinoma likes to go into the blood.
And chorial carcinoma very quickly goes into the blood.
And so these are the four carcinomas
that are the key exceptions.
We talked about that in the neoplasia chapter.
Medullary carcinoma is a malignant proliferation of C cells.
The C cells normally sit adjacent to the follicles
within the thyroid.
This tumor is associated with high levels of calcitonin.
And that's because the C cells normally make calcitonin.
Now remember that calcitonin can lower the calcium
by causing renal excretion.
However, at physiologic levels, it's normally inactive.
But with these high levels produced by the tumor,
you can actually get hypocalcemia.
In addition, because you're producing so much calcitonin,
some of that calcitonin can actually deposit
within the tumor as amyloid.
And this would be an example of localized amyloidosis.
And in fact, I covered this in our amyloid lectures.
And so here's a classic picture.
And the high yield is that you have these malignant tumor cells
within this amyloid stroma.
Notice all this pink material here is all amyloid.
And so again, if you did a fine neal aspiration
and you pulled out a little bit of tissue,
you would see malignant cells in an amyloid stroma.
Very high yield description.
Malignant cells in an amyloid stroma.
Now, it's also high yield to note
that there are some familial cases
of medullary carcinoma of the thyroid.
These are associated with MEN2A and MEN2B.
Now, MEN refers to multiple endocrine neoplasia,
and this is when you get neoplasia
within multiple endocrine organs.
In MEN2A, you get medullary carcinoma of the thyroid,
which we're talking about here,
pheochromocytoma, which we'll talk about later,
and parathyroid adenomas,
which we'll also talk about later.
In MEN2B, you get medullary carcinoma of the thyroid,
pheochromocytoma, and ganglioneuromas,
particularly of the oral mucosa.
Now, in both of these, MEN2A and 2B,
you're gonna get medullary carcinoma of the thyroid,
and that really is the key cancer
that these patients get.
Now, what's very high yield to note,
particularly for the purpose of board exam,
is that when patients have familial cases
of medullary carcinoma of the thyroid,
it's classically associated with a mutation
in the RET oncogene.
Now, this is important because if you suspect
a familial predisposition to medullary carcinoma of the thyroid,
you can test the patients for RET mutation.
If there is a RET mutation,
the patient can elect to remove the thyroid prophylactically
to remove the risk of medullary carcinoma of the thyroid.
Very high yield because it has major clinical implications.
So, if there is a RET mutation
and you're suspecting a familial case
of medullary carcinoma of the thyroid,
that will then lead to prophylactic thyroidectomy.
The last carcinoma is anaplastic carcinoma.
Remember, papillary, follicular, medullary, anaplastic.
Anaplastic is an undifferentiated malignant tumor
of the thyroid, classically seen in the elderly.
Now, this cancer is highly malignant,
and so it invades local structures
and can lead to dysphagia or respiratory compromise.
Now, this would lead to a clinical scenario
that is very similar to Rydell's fibrosing thyroiditis.
However, remember that in Rydell's fibrosing thyroiditis,
it would be in a younger patient,
classically a younger female,
whereas in anaplastic carcinoma,
you're thinking about the elderly.
In addition, of course, you could do a biopsy.
In anaplastic carcinoma,
you would see these highly malignant cells
that don't resemble anything
that would normally be present within the thyroid,
and that's what the word anaplastic means,
that you've got a very undifferentiated tumor
that's not really forming any normal structures.
And with that point,
we conclude our discussion of the thyroid gland.